{"tossups": [{"question": "This woman nearly fell over during a botched curtsy in front of King George VI. This woman was sent to Craig House in 1941 and was later relocated to St. Coletta School for Exceptional Children, where she spent the last 66 years of her life. Eunice Shriver founded the Special Olympics in honor of this woman, who underwent a failed lobotomy 22 years before the assassination of her brother John. For ten points, name this member of the Kennedy family.", "answer": "<b> Rose</b>mary<b> Kennedy</b> (or<b> Rose</b> Marie<b> Kennedy</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "One side\u2019s strategy in this event was later replicated in Operations Ariel and Cycle, which targeted Le Havre and Cherbourg. In anticipation of this event, 26 May was declared a national day of prayer by George VI. Codenamed Operation Dynamo, this event\u2019s success relied upon \u201clittle ships\u201d such as yachts and civilian fishing boats that crossed the English Channel. For ten points, identify this \u201cmiracle\u201d in which the British Expeditionary Force was evacuated from a French beach.", "answer": "evacuation from<b> Dunkirk</b> (accept descriptive answers that mention<b> Dunkirk</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Gaspar Gorricio helped this man compile the Book of Prophecies. While traveling with the Pinz\u00b4on brothers, this man encountered the chief Guacanagari. This subject of the Capitulations of Santa Fe was replaced by Francisco de Bobadilla as governor of the Indies. The 400th anniversary of his most notable achievement was commemorated by the 1893 Chicago World\u2019s Fair. For ten points, name this Genoan-born explorer who commanded the Ni\u02dcna, the Pinta, and the Santa Maria to the New World.", "answer": "Christopher<b> Columbus</b> (or Cristofor<b> Colombo</b>; or Crist\u00b4obal<b> Col\u00b4on</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "While working for this government, an orphaned radio specialist aids in the hunt for the Sea of Flame jewel in Anthony Doerr\u2019s Pulitzer-winning novel<em> All the Light We Cannot See</em>. Annemarie Johansen fools a canine unit employed by this government using a basket laced with cocaine in a novel in which a group of refugees flee to Sweden from this government\u2019s reach. For ten points, Lois Lowry\u2019s novel<em> Number the</em> <em>Stars</em> is set during what government\u2019s occupation of Denmark in 1943?", "answer": "<b> Nazi Germany</b> (accept either underlined portion; accept the<b> Third Reich</b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Heged\u00a8us Reforms attempted to combat the effects of this phenomenon as Hungary faced it in the aftermath of the Treaty of Trianon. Another instance of this phenomenon was sparked by a general strike in the Ruhr. J.P. Morgan Jr. co-led a conference that sought a solution to that instance of this phenomenon, in which the Reichsbank produced notes worth 100 trillion marks. For ten points, name this type of destabilization of the value of a currency, famously experienced by the Weimar [vye-mar] Republic.", "answer": "(hyper)<b>inflation</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man was advised in his waning years by a group known as the Rolex 12, and he previously suppressed a wave of student protests called the First Quarter Storm. This leader, who attempted to create a \u201cNew Society\u201d in the model of Suharto, ordered the assassination of a political rival in an airport in 1983; that rival\u2019s wife, Corazon, succeeded this man after he was toppled in the 1986 People Power Revolution. For ten points, name this corrupt former Philippine president whose wife Imelda owned a famous shoe collection.", "answer": "Ferdinand<b> Marcos</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Before the recognition of these objects as important artifacts in 1899, many of them were ground into dust and used as a cure for malaria. A sixty day cycle using the Heavenly Stems and Earthly Branches was used to record data from these objects. Heated metal rods were used to crack these objects, on which questions were written. For ten points, name these objects that were used as divination tools used by Shang dynasty oracles whose common examples included ox scapulas.", "answer": "oracle<b> bone</b>s (accept turtle<b> shell</b>s; accept ox<b> scapula</b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Misc Science"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Three works of art from this country appear in the background of a painting of the art supplier P`ere Tanguy [\u201cpear\u201d tan-ghee]. A work from this country showing plum branches was copied in an oil painting that added an orange border with nonsensical characters. A wood-based art form from this country was introduced to van Gogh and other European artists after trade with the Dutch was opened on the artificial island of Dejima. For ten points, name this home country of the artists Hiroshige and Hokusai, who painted<em> Thirty-Six Views of Mount Fuji</em>.", "answer": "<b> Japan</b> or<b> Nippon</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "When this man\u2019s son vomited his poison, his assassins hired the wrestler Narcissus to strangle him in the bath, leading to the ascent of Pertinax. A book by this man partly written in Carnuntum tells the reader to \u201cnot then consider life a thing of any value\u201d and may have been inspired by the works of Epictetus. This father of Commodus ruled alongside Lucius Verus in the second century AD. For ten points, name this last member of the Five Good Emperors and author of the<em> Meditations</em>.", "answer": "<b> Marcus Aurelius</b> Antoninus Augustus", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "Royal Dutch Shell was sued by people from this country after Ogoniland protesters, including Ken Saro-Wiwa and the Ogoni 9, were killed. In 2009, a group in this country besieged a Bauchi police station, instigating clashes that killed its leader Mohammed Yusuf; that group\u2019s current leader, Abubakar Shekau, rebranded that group as the Islamic State in West Africa after pledging allegiance to ISIS. In 2014, over 200 schoolgirls were kidnapped in Chibok in, for ten points, what African country where Boko Haram bombed the UN building in Abuja in 2011?", "answer": "<b> Nigeria</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {"question": "The Porteous Riots occurred after the death of an ally of this man, Queen Caroline. This man put forth the requirement that all plays were to be reviewed by the Lord Chamberlain, probably because he disliked his caricaturization as Mr. Peachum in John Gay\u2019s<em> The Beggar\u2019s Opera</em>. This man was forced to resign from the Parliament after losing the War of Jenkins\u2019 Ear. For ten points, name this man, usually considered the first Prime Minister of Great Britain.", "answer": "Sir Robert<b> Walpole</b>, First Earl of<b> Orford</b> (accept either or both names)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "During this President\u2019s administration, Southern senators limited federal use of domestic troops via the Posse Comitatus Act. A department in Paraguay is named for this President, who awarded Gran Chaco to Paraguay after the War of the Triple Alliance. This President promised to pull federal troops from the South to win an election after he lost the popular vote to Samuel Tilden. For ten points, name this man whose Presidency was assured by the Compromise of 1877.", "answer": "Rutherford B.<b> Hayes</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>The third movement of this piece includes an unusual solo for the fourth horn player, and another section features the cellos and basses dismissing melodies from earlier movements.</b> <b>One of this piece\u2019s melodies was adapted for the (+)</b> <b>anthem of both the unrecognized</b> <b>state of Rhodesia and of the European Union. This piece\u2019s final movement, dubbed a (*)</b>\u201csymphony-within-a-symphony,\u201d features the lyric \u201cO friends, not these tones!\u201d and adapted a Friedrich Schiller poem, \u201cOde to Joy.\u201d For ten points, name this final symphony by Ludwig van Beethoven.", "answer": "Ludwig van<b> Beethoven\u2019s Symphony #9</b> in D minor, opus 125 (or<b> \u201cChoral\u201d</b> Symphony;\u201cSymphony\u201d and \u201cBeethoven\u201d are not necessary after each is mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>As a lieutenant-colonel, this man led a bayonet charge on the left flank during the Battle of Mallavelly before failing in his first attack on Seringapatam in the Anglo-Mysore War.</b> <b>This resident of Apsley House threatened to (+)</b> <b>resign if the Catholic Relief Act of 1829</b> <b>was not passed; that unpopular decision that may have contributed to his nickname of (*)</b>\u201cIron Duke.\u201d In another battle, this man famously said that either \u201cnight or the Prussians must come;\u201dBl\u00a8ucher\u2019s Prussians did. For ten points, name this English general who defeated Napoleon at Waterloo.", "answer": "Arthur<b> Wellesley</b>, first Duke of<b> Wellington</b> (accept either)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This company\u2019s questionable business tactics were revealed in the Halloween documents. This company managed to avoid paying any royalty fees to Spyglass by giving one of</b> <b>their products away for free. The CEO of this company was said to be (+)</b> <b>\u201cevasive and</b> <b>unresponsive\u201d during a deposition in which he repeatedly said \u201cI don\u2019t recall.\u201d Thomas Penfield Jackson ordered the (*)</b> breakup of this company in 1999, a ruling that was later reversed and settled. For ten points, name this company that was sued by the US government for monopolizing the computer industry by bundling Internet Explorer with the Windows operating system.", "answer": "<b> Microsoft</b> Corporation", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>A ruler of this group named Reccared I converted to Christianity. The Suebi Kingdom was conquered and annexed by these people. The Muslim conquest of these people began</b> <b>after the Battle of Guadelete, where King (+)</b> <b>Roderic was killed. The Reconquista began</b> <b>Roderic was killed. The Reconquista began</b> <b>under Pelagius, a leader of this group, which had earlier defeated (*)</b> <b>under Pelagius, a leader of this group, which had earlier defeated (*)</b> Rome at the Battle of Adrianople. The Roman province of Hispania was home to the kingdom of these people, who established a capital at Toledo. For ten points, name this eastern Gothic group, led by Alaric, that conquered modern-day Spain.", "answer": "<b> Visigoth</b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This man ordered Gideon Pillow to fix official reports that gave Pillow too much credit for this man\u2019s victories. This man negotiated with James Douglas after a bloodless war over</b> <b>the San Juan Islands, the (+)</b> <b>Pig War. This man headed the US Navy\u2019s intimidation of</b> <b>South Carolina during the Nullification Crisis. This general, who led the first large-scale American (*)</b> amphibious attack in 1847, proposed blockading the Confederacy in the Anaconda Plan. For ten points, name this victor at Veracruz, a general nicknamed \u201cOld Fuss and Feathers.\u201d", "answer": "Winfield<b> Scott</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>This location was the site of a massive gold shield until it was looted by the Jat people. Lapis lazuli from the walls of this location was looted by British regulars, though Lord (+) Curzon later ordered the restoration of this building. The Mahtab Bagh was discovered near this building, giving rise to a myth that it was supposed to be adjacent to a twin building made of (*) </b> black stone. A raised reflecting pool sits in front of this location, which was designed as a burial place for Mumtaz. For ten points, name this white marble mausoleum commissioned by Shah Jahan of India.", "answer": "<b> Taj Mahal</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In a battle during this war, Marguerite Higgins photographed Baldomero L\u00b4opez scaling a seawall before his death. Human wave tactics were used during this war\u2019s Battle of</b> <b>Heartbreak (+)</b> <b>Ridge. During this war, American forces were trapped at the Chosin</b> <b>Reservoir and F-86 Sabres fought in (*)</b> \u201cMiG Alley.\u201d Douglas MacArthur was relieved by President Truman during, for ten points, what 1950s war that ended with a demilitarized zone being established on an East Asian peninsula?", "answer": "<b> Korea</b>n War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}